So let's say somebody has come to terms
with the fact that they need to keep the
precepts and be celibate if they want to
get the right view, but they still
struggle to understand what they're
supposed to quote unquote do as a
practice, if not meditate in the modern
sense, because the precepts obviously
don't tell you what to do. It's just a
list of things to not do. And once you
no longer do those things, you still
have all this time left. So how can you
describe the practice for such a person?
>> Well, they already described it really.
Uh precepts are about about the things
that you won't do
and you need to protect that for as long
as your main mode of doing
is concerned not about what do I do, but
about what is it that I don't do and
what I won't do. regardless of what
comes my way.
That's what it means. Being established
in virtue does not mean I learned the
precepts and and and kept them
religiously for so long. Means basically
my values have shifted in a sense that
doesn't matter what happens to me, what
experience occurs, novelty, pleasant,
unpleasant, doubtful,
I might well not know what to do, what
to say, uh how to react. But I will know
what not to do.
Like I have no doubt about that because
I've been purifying that beforehand. So
that's why when you take on the precepts
yes you take them on by body you take
them on through the external form but
the whole point is so that you can
implement them on the mental level
as I said killing stealing uh um
celibacy non-seacy all these things
basically you take on these precepts and
then yes you stop engaging with those
things with the body but then how is
your mind do you revolve around it like
throughout your day thinking hateful
thoughts feeding them oh but I'm not
killing anybody, but I'm I'm wishing I I
could or I or I or I am. Same with way.
Same with um uh sensuality. Oh, I I am
withdrawn physically, but do I allow my
mind to wallow and and fantasize about
stuff? It's like, oh, I should really
upgrade that and not allow it on that
level because that's where the physical
restraint is supposed to lead to. you
confining your mind within the
beneficial behaviors
all while
dampening and refraining from giving in
to the pressuring tendency to do
something about it to do something about
the practice to to meditate but but
surely I must do something palpable
because all of that is just perpetuation
of your own craving
all of that is The syllabas
doesn't matter if it's concerned with
sila or with duty. My duty is to
meditate. It's like no your duty is to understand
It's like no your duty is to understand
the dharma. Whenever people in sutas
meditate monks meditate when they
translate that again colored with a
contemporary terraada the views of watch
your nostrils and focus three feet in
front of you and squint through your
eyes as if these things are relevant to
to to anything or anyone. Um
whenever they say meditate that's where
they kind of like to imply oh that's
what it means but when the sut says
meditate they mean like go on and
clarify things that are not clear. Why
are you still subject to suffering? Why
are you taking things as yours uh that
cause you to suffer? Why can you not
withdraw from sensuality? Why are you
still relishing the pleasure that can be
obtained through your body? There's like
myriad of aspects and options you could
you could you could contemplate every
single day. you could meditate on every
single day.
Says a monk go sickness, aging, death.
Exactly. Says a monk goes to an empty
heart says as this heart is empty of
others, so is this experience empty of
of the owner.
Like what what meditation technique is
that? It's not an empty visualizations
how vuda visuda tries to present it.
Just think these images and clay discs
and whatnot. No, it's genuinely like
this experience here and now. It's empty
of an owner. I have a sense of
ownership. I'm not denying it. But that
sense of ownership cannot be mine.
Now, that's not necessarily hard to
understand. People can wrap their head
around. But whether it will land on a
dimension where it matters or not, well,
that depends whether their behavior has
been purified beforehand.
I have they withdrawn themselves from
sensuality from the five hindrances
and that's the basic satipana by the way
these contemplations in regard to the
body feeling mind that's what satipana
is that's why the Buddha says the one
way only that leads to the purification
of being that leads to fulfillment of of
the um seven enlightenment factors
fulfillment of of mindfulness
fulfillment of um of of the dharma dhama
vichaya fulfillment of the energy and
everything The fulfillment of samadei
like samadei as in uh state of composure
that comes on the basis of padi and calm
is the result of clearly delineating
non-ownership letting go vaga that that
abandoning of the five hindrances and
all of that and actually there are says
a monk abandons the five well gradual
trains withdraws from sensuality all of
that and then abandons the hindrances is
and then can practice satipatana
to bring all these things to
fulfillment. But generally is just completely as I
But generally is just completely as I
said yeah but I must do something
beforehand and to be fair as I said most
of the if not all of the ter world today
it is presenting it that way because
that's even how the visiago originally
presented it all these corruptions could
be traced back to this commentaries
really whereby it's like no no no it
doesn't matter the basis doesn't matter
which you are just keep stabbing in the
dark and just keep doing these things
randomly um practice the the sensation watching
um practice the the sensation watching
calming
visualizations, practices and stuff,
stuff stuff and sort of kind of make
them sound like they come from the
sutras uh and then it will happen.
Yet again you read the sutas and it's a
clear purification of behavior, speech
and mind that results in uh an enduring
nonforgetfulness that then uh brings the joy. The
that then uh brings the joy. The
blamelessness virtue brings the
blamelessness brings the joy brings the
calm brings samadei. There is no
introduction there of oh and then do
this and then do that and it's like a
very different
uh flavor to it than if you just go on
your generic kind of uh mindfulness of
breathing retreat today where is it
doesn't matter where you come from
doesn't matter the level of of what
precepts you you hold what what
commitment you have to the practice just
do these practice of of of artificial
calming squinting closing your eyes
visualizing and the truth will reveal
itself self that's just like well I bet
even the mysticism of the Buddhist time
like the wrong views of the Buddhist
time they had like a mystical inning
were not as shallow as that
had probably more to it had at least
some form of purification implied
>> well to be fair even the visi assumes
that you're a monkhu
>> it doesn't actually encourage those
practices for lay people
>> well there you go I apologize to visa Yeah.
Yeah.
>> And also a person may not realize that
uh when they don't have unh wholesome
states present in their mind that is
also uh a work that they have to do to
not let themselves fall into doing more
as if you know there's there's kind of
I always need to be purifying something.
>> Yeah.
>> I always got to be doing something. My
duty is waiting constantly. No. Exactly.
Yeah, it's a skill that needs to be de
developed on account of not giving into
that pressure of craving to be doing
constantly and resolving doubts and
stuff. No, no, no, hold on. Things have
a reason. I'm not acting out. Yes, there
is a pressure to what? To understand or
to get rid of or to replace discomfort
with comfort. All these intentions are
already there. You're not seeing them.
And because of that, you won't see when
you are actually in a wholesome state
that you don't need to do anything
about. You just need to prevent from
slipping from
that's why I said uh the true correctly
practice mindfulness it's effortless and
the suta says you can't have too much of
of sati you can't overdo it
you can't have too much of not
forgetting about important things but as
I said so many times even that's
corrupted today through the same
principle of you know uh people through
like whatever mystical learning
self-hypnotic practices then try to read
the sutras with those sort of framework
glasses on and then they they see these
things in the sutras that are not there
such as mindfulness means memory means
nonforgetfulness. So ask yourself in the same sense like
So ask yourself in the same sense like
in in a colloquial sense what does it
mean to not be forgetful?
Does it mean like focusing on every
second of my experience dayto-day
watching everything in front of my eyes?
It's like no by any stretch like even if
you want to try to do that in order to
not forget things you'll forget things.
So how do you not forget?
What technique do you do when you
remember and then you realize oh you for not
and then you realize oh you for not
forget basically when things are
important to you can't forget even if
you want. So make them important
make the precepts important. Make the
breaking of precepts dangerous. make
make it dangerous to act out of unh
wholesome states feel that danger
mindfulness is growing
and that's just how it works as I said
in day-to-day life in everyone's life
like nonforgetfulness
is not something you do yet as I said
everything that kind of becomes
spiritual is allowed to mean what it
doesn't mean so nonforggetfulness
mindfulness doesn't mean that anymore it
means a special focusing satipatana
meditation hypnotic calming practice.
It's like
that will actually make you forget
things that will make you absor
completely absorbed and oblivious to
your experience as a whole. uh as I said
in the other talk uh understanding
understanding of stuff like in a
colloquial sense you everybody know okay
understanding means like getting the
meaning understanding seeing for
yourself whereby you can explain it in
your own words uh you can you could sort
of uh see it regardless of you know
where you learned it from and stuff you
could see it for yourself and even put
it in your own terms in that sense but
then when it was taken into the
spiritual context understanding doesn't
mean that anymore it just means anything
and nothing means a novelty experience
understanding of the of the of the now
and the the isness of the things and
stuff like that. It's like what do you
understand there? But all these things
are called to understanding. Oh, he
develops understanding by having a
special meditation experience. We
haven't understood anything. You just
went through some novelty.
Some novelty that you perceive through
your senses basically.